<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A two-inch board for M. Prynne to peep thorow being a full and satisfactory answer to a late libellous pamphlet ... called, A declaration of the officers and armies illegall &amp;c. proceedings and practices against the XI impeached members ... : with ... a justification of the armies charge and proceedings against the XI impeached members, by law, president, and reason : with certaine considerable queries and observations upon the cities late tumultuous rebellious proceedings agaisnt the Parliament / vvritten by T.R., Gent.</title>
            <author>T. R., Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58482</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R92</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11143</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13012150</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13012150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96497</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58482)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96497)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 397:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A two-inch board for M. Prynne to peep thorow being a full and satisfactory answer to a late libellous pamphlet ... called, A declaration of the officers and armies illegall &amp;c. proceedings and practices against the XI impeached members ... : with ... a justification of the armies charge and proceedings against the XI impeached members, by law, president, and reason : with certaine considerable queries and observations upon the cities late tumultuous rebellious proceedings agaisnt the Parliament / vvritten by T.R., Gent.</title>
                  <author>T. R., Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prynne, William, 1600-1669. --  Declaration of the officers and armies, illegall, injurious proceedings and practises against the XI impeached members.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96497:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A two-inch Board for</hi> M. Prynne <hi>to peep thorow:</hi> Being a full and ſatisfactory ANSWER To a late libellous Pamphlet (herein proved to bee his) called, A DECLARATION OF <hi>The Officers and Armies illegall</hi> &amp;c. <hi>proceedings and practices against the XI. impeached Members:</hi> And to other that Authors ſcandalous Papers lately publiſhed, purpoſely to aſperſe the Army and their proceedings. <hi>WITH</hi> A diſcoverie of his lies, ſubtilties, and deluſions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and a Juſtification of the Armies Charge and proceedings againſt the XI. impeached Members, by Law, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, and Reaſon. WITH Certaine conſiderable Queries and obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the Cities late tumultuous rebellious proceedings againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p>VVritten by <hi>T. R.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro. 26.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Anſwer a foole in his folly, leaſt he be wiſe in his own conceit.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeere 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:96497:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96497:2"/>
               <head>A two-inch Board for M. <hi>Prynne</hi> to peep thorough, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THe Declarer (whether M. <hi>Pryn</hi> or whoſoever) tells us in his introductorie part of his Declaration, how quondam great <hi>Cromwell,</hi> Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> loſt his head by an illegall Law or Preſident, which himſelfe procured <hi>to ſuſpend from, and attaint others in Parliament upon meere generall accuſations, without particular proofs, and before anſwer given,</hi> intimating, and in his ſubſequent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, audaciouſly and falſly affirming, that the Army have done the like againſt the eleven Members, therefore <hi>this perillous Preſident ſhould admoniſh ſome of the Earls name</hi> (Lievtenant-Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> hee means) and the reſt of the Army &amp;c. it being a memorable Maxime of a learned Judge Sir <hi>Edw. Cooke, That the more high and abſolute the Juriſdiction of the high Court of Parliament is, the more juſt and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it ought to be in the proceedings, and to give example of juſtice to inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Courts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the Army have neither ſuſpended nor attainted any upon meer generall accuſations, for they have brought in particular Articles of Treaſon and miſdemeanour againſt them, and expect daily a Plea or Anſwer to them, that they may proceed unto triall and produce their proofes, upon which they doubt not but to have them attainted and convicted alſo: and therefore truly, neither Lievtenant-Generall <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> nor any other Officer or Member of the Army need to feare (nor can they incurre) any ſuch danger by this juſt and legall accuſation, as unhappily happened to <hi>Cromwell</hi> the great, unleſſe he or they ſhould unhappily fall under the power of Mr. Declarer, or thoſe he declares for, who indeed have uſed like unjuſt, arbitrary practices, as that <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> did, nay worſe: for they have occaſioned and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many a one to be ſuſpended and impriſoned without any charge or accuſation at all. I will not inſtance, becauſe everie man knowes it, even thou thy ſelfe, O Declarer. And if the eleven Members were ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as great <hi>Cromwell</hi> was, to wit, not only ſuſpended, but executed (the which nevertheleſſe I deſire not, nor is it, I am ſure, either endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured or intended) without any anſwer or proofe produced, it was but juſt upon them, <hi>Lex talionis:</hi> for they and their Accomplices have done the ſame to others, though not to deprivation of life, yet of, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, propriety and eſtate, equivalent to life, and was there any more then a generall charge at firſt given in againſt <hi>Strafford</hi> and <hi>Canterbury,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96497:3"/>upon which they were preſently reſtrained? And by how much the more ſuperlative the Parliament ought to be in juſtice above other Courts, for that its power and Juriſdiction is ſo; ſo much the more vile and ſhamefull, culpable and condemnable are thoſe Members thereof, who have been more impious and unjuſt in the uſe and the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of that power, then the moſt contemptible Officers of the meaneſt and loweſt Courts, of Judicature. And where now, I pray you, is the parallel M. Declarer, inſtances of illegalitie and arbitrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, between the Lord <hi>Cromwells</hi> Attainder, and the proceedings of the Army, and in particular of Lievtenant-Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> which he names there in ſpeciall, againſt the eleven juſtly accuſed Members? So much in anſwer to his Introduction. Now to his particulars, by which hee pretends to demonſtrate the unjuſtneſſe of the Armies proſecution.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The unjuſtneſſe thereof he ſaith appears <hi>by the generality and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of the Accuſers, the charge againſt them being preſented in the name of the whole Army, without the hands of any particular perſons to it, who will undertake at their perills to make it good, or elſe to give the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Members and Houſe due reparations if they faile to doe it, contrary to the Common and Statute Law of the Land.</hi> Was it not in the name of his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> the head in particular, and of the Army in generall as of a Bodie, owned by all, and preſented by ſome of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Members thereof in name of the whole? A way and uſage moſt certaine and ſure: had it come in theſe words, viz. in the name of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine perſons, or of the generall and major part of the Army, it had been juſtly chargeable with incertainty: But what act can carry with it more certainty, then that which hath the joynt-concurrence of an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Bodie, or Community? Hath not the practice of the Houſe of Commons for forme and manner in things of the ſame nature, been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſame? and did not they impeach <hi>Strafford, Canterbury,</hi> Judge <hi>Bartlet, Finch, Windebanck</hi> and others, this preſent Parliament in the ſame generall uncertaine manner, in the name of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and of all the Commons of England? And if this of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> and the Army be unjuſt, ſo then was that; if that was juſt, ſo then is this: the matter is the ſame, and the manner is the ſame, and there is more ille gality and incertainety in the factious Petitions and Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances heretofore preſented by the pretended Lord Mayor, Aldermen and Common Councell in name of the City, (which the City never owned) then in this Charge, preferred in the name of, and owned by the whole Army: and there is no dread M. Declarer, but his Excellency &amp;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96497:3"/>the Army will make good their charge againſt the accuſed to their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and your ſhame, and I doubt not, but you who are ſo much now in their behalfe for reparations, according to Law before the iſſue bee proved, will then be enforced, according to your own litigious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, to make reparations to his Excellencie and the Army for all your pernicious, ſeditious, falſe, ſcandalons, notorious, ſhameleſſe reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, revilings, imputations, accuſations, and aſperſions, publiſhed and uttered in your invenomed Declaration againſt them and theſe their juſt, legall, and honourable proceedings, which are ſo much affected, honoured and promoted by all in generall, unleſſe it be ſuch as are alike guilty and deſperately wicked, who neither feare God, nor love their King or their Countrey.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The unjuſtneſſe of the Armies proceedings, he ſaith, appeares <hi>by the incertainety and generality of the charge it ſelfe in meere generall and ambiguous termes, to which the parties accuſed can give no anſwer nor make anie defence, and thereupon voted inſufficient by the Houſe,</hi> 25. <hi>Junii to charge or ſuſpend them by the Law of the Land.</hi> Here note, that he meanes the generall heads of the Charge, given in 15 June laſt, and not the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Charge which came in Tueſday 6. July, although like a Juggler he inſerts it in ſuch a ſort as to have the multitude believe it the ſame. And as for the generall heads, there was no anſwer thereunto required, onely therefore a ſuſpertion of the accuſed, as being charged, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with M. Declarers leave, there was both reaſon and preſident for it, although the Houſe voted againſt it. Look backe and conſider the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments proceedings in all times againſt their Members in ſuch caſes, and in particular in the laſt and lateſt preſidents, <hi>Strafford, Canterbury, Barkley,</hi> &amp;c. nay have not the Fouſe of Commons ſuſpended and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded divers of their owne Members this Parliament, for words and particular actions in the Houſe, caſes of inferiour nature and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, to the matter of charge againſt the 11 Members? And againe, if thoſe generall heads, five in number againſt the 11. Members (which are more large and ſpeciall then the generall charge the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons preferred againſt the E. of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and B. of <hi>Canterbury</hi>) were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient to charge or ſuſpend them, of what validitie then were thoſe generall charges of the H. of Commons, ſo vehemently proſecuted by ſome of theſe very 11. whereupon <hi>Strafford</hi> and <hi>Canterbury</hi> were both charged and ſuſpended, yea and ſecured, which theſe vipers are not? what juſtice then, I ſay, in their caſe, had thoſe two and others? Peace for ſhame good M. Simpleton, it is an ill bird that bewrayes her own neſt, you will help to enlarge their charge by and by, and while you plead like a mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for their juſtification, you will, like a fool, lay more guilt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation upon them.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96497:4"/>
               <p n="3">3. The unjuſtneſſe of the Armies proceedings aginſt the 11. Members, he faith, appeares by <hi>the multitude and quality of the parties impeached, eleven at once, all men of approved integrity, fidelity, and abilities,</hi> and there in <hi>this third inſtance,</hi> he tells you of all their good acts, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larges their praiſe beyond their deſerts. A ſilly argument without ſenſe or reaſon, to prove the unjuſtneſſe of the charge by the multitude and qualitie of perſons accuſed, as if a multitude, and thoſe men eminent both for eſtates and authority, could not act treaſon, or be as culpable of criminall treſpaſſes, as the poor and meane: What thinke ye of the Complotters and Actors of the Gunpowder plot, the riſing by the Earle of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and his confederates in the North, in the Reigne of Queen <hi>Elizabeth? Abſalom</hi> and all the heads of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple againſt King <hi>David?</hi> Here were as great multitudes and as gallant men in theſe traiterous actions, as any of theſe 11. Members: truly, I never thinke of M. <hi>Hollis,</hi> the principall of the eleven, but I call to mind <hi>Cataline</hi> of Rome, whoſe ſole ambition was to be the head of a faction, though it turned to his ruine: as for M. <hi>Maſſey</hi> we know he is a good Souldier, but no Chriſtian; and if the number and the quality be a ſufficient excuſe to theſe eleven, and of condemnation to their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers, Sir <hi>Tho.</hi> &amp; the Army for injuſtice againſt them, Oh how unjuſt then were all the proceedings againſt all the aforeſaid in thoſe daies! but I wil ask this <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> whether he ever heard or read of any grand treaſon, (for the 11. Members actions, as ſleight as he and other knaves &amp; fooles make of them, when they come to the teſt, wilbe found no other, even exceeding <hi>Straffords,</hi> and in effect equall to that of the Gunpowder) wherein there was not more then a few, and thoſe no mean ones, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates? Nay do not ſuch abominable actions evermore accompanie the greateſt perſonages and ſpirits? for mean men have neither wit, power, opportunity or audacity, to contrive or act them, and therfore are never tempted (unleſſe by ſo great ones to be inſtruments) to doe them. And as for their abilities, and acts of merit, by how much the more able, and by ſo much the more wicked, therefore by ſo much the more odible and condemnable. The Devill hath as exquiſite gifts and endowments, and more then any mortall, yet not therefore to be either pittied or juſtified: and for the good they or any of them have done, why did not they continue in it? who hindered them? Not to him that runs, but to him that holds out to the end of the race, belong's the praiſe: <hi>Finis coronat factum:</hi> Juſtice (is like death) it takes a man as it findes him, it conſidereth neither quality nor condition, what a man was, is, or hath done, but of what he is accuſed and found guilty; and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96497:4"/>ſo it rendreth unto him, either by acquitting or condemning him. The old Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes had deſerved as well of the Kingdome, and was much more honoured and beloved of the people, then ever any of theſe 11. Members, yet ye know his end; he being found guilty, juſtice forgot his former good ſervices; his honour was tainted, and all his merits were forfeited: and this manner of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is juſtified by the example of God the moſt juſt Judge of quick and dead, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.24. Nor are theſe men of ſuch great eminencie and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in themſelves, as they are by that authority wherewith we have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted them as our Truſtees, the which they have unworthily and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfully perverted and abuſed, M. <hi>Hollis</hi> is the moſt honourable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, but by the evill of his actions is ſo much the more diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable; for <hi>nobilitas est unica virtus:</hi> and the reſt do we not know them? The Merchants of Hamborough can tell you of <hi>Maſſie,</hi> his manners and his quality; and without queſtion there are thoſe can give as true a character of the reſt, as Mr. Declarer or any other. As for the Houſe clearing any of them by Vote, or M. <hi>Prynnes</hi> (who never knew aright how to examine or caſt up any accompt) acquitting them in their accompts, is of no value, <hi>non valet ova duo:</hi> For if an illegall factious Vote may clean any Member of an accuſation of breach of Law, or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique truſt, where then is Englands Law? <hi>dic quaeſo.</hi> No Sir, he that is accuſed to tranſgreſſe the Law, muſt be acquit or condemned by the Law, in a publike Judicatory, and not by arbitrary Votes within a cloſe room and private walls: <hi>Strafford</hi> and all traitors and treſpaſſers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the publike, have been alwaies tried publikely; and ſo it is juſt, legall and meet theſe ſhould be. As for the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee for Accompts, their acquitting men by<note n="*" place="margin">As Sir W. <hi>Lewis</hi> was by name.</note> Vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that is, if they bring in but one or two, though they be ſuborned to ſweare that their falſe accompts are true, is of as much credit and value, as a thieſs procuring witneſſes to avouch a ſtolne horſe, for which notwithſtanding he may be hanged.</p>
               <p>As for his fourth inſtance of the Armies violence to have the eleven Members ſuſpended before any reall particular charge or proofs produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt them, taxing the Army with threatning the Houſe by their Remonſtrance, June 23. if they would not ſuſpend them upon their (as he ſaith) illegall impeachment. And what M. Declarer, if the Army did require the ſuſpenſion of them before any particular charge exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? It was not before their generall charge was delivered, which was not onely in its ſelfe more parricular and ſpeciall, I tell you, then the generall charges given in by the Houſe of Commons (which ſome of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96497:5"/>theſe accuſed were then violent promoters of) againſt <hi>Strafford</hi> and <hi>Canterbury,</hi> but ſufficient and legall alſo, or els thoſe againſt <hi>Strafford</hi> and <hi>Canterb.</hi> were not. Truly M. Declarer, while you ſtrike at the Army, the ſtroak falls upon your own friends, you ſtill make their caſe worſe: And as for proofs, would you have them produced before the accuſed have anſwered? Did the H. of Commons do ſo in the caſes aforeſaid? no, nor deliver in any particular charge in many moneths after, and yet both the Earl and the Biſhop were preſently not only ſuſpended, but committed alſo; and ſo are not theſe 11. traiterous men, though there be particular Articles, and thoſe no ſmall and light ones, nor ſo uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and dubious, as moſt of theirs were againſt <hi>Strafford</hi> and <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> theſe are all for traiterous and unjuſt arbitrary actions, thoſe were many of them for traiterous and arbitrary words and intentions; theſe are all for matter of fact, thoſe were onely many of them for diſcourſe purpoſe; and ſpeech. And good M. Declarer, do not abuſe your calling and your knowledg too, for I know you are a Lawyer, and M. <hi>Prynne</hi> by name, if I be not miſtaken, your ſtile, your termes, and your venome declare ſo. What Law is there, either common or Statute in this Kingdome or elſwhere, that requires the production of witneſſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the accuſed have pleaded and made their defence? Do not men in all caſes and cauſes, civill and criminall, whether true or falſe, firſt put in Baile, or ſubmit to reſtraint, to anſwer the action bill or complaint, againſt them, and then after they are charged, put in their Plea or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and ſo joyne iſſue for triall, and then the Plaintiffe or Proſecuter, brings in his evidence or profs? Is not this the common and conſtant, yea, the true and legal courſe in all Courts of Judicature, and at all Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Aſſizes throughout the Kingdome? if there was any other, your Margent, I am ſure, would ſhew it us, for you are full of your quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though they be feigned and falſe, making a faire ſhew (like many poore beggarly tradeſmen) upon the ſtall, when alas there is little or nothing of any worth within: but you think, that by theſe meanes, the Army, to ſtop your ſcandalous clamours, wil like fools be provoked to declare their wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes before hand, that ſo you may tamper with them, &amp; by indirect wares either per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, deter, or divert them. Stay good M. Declarer, your Worſhip, as I tel you, is no good Accomptant, you are too ſhort in your reckoning. Nor do the Armie uſe anie threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as you ſay M. Declarer: in that, to ſpeak plain truth, you declare your ſelf a liar, &amp; by this ſure token I know your name is <hi>Prynne:</hi> for in their Remonſtrance is; Iune; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſhewed, that whereas they had exhibited their Charge againſt the 11 Members, and made mame other propoſalls conducing to the ſettlement and ſafene of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Kingdom, the Houſes ſleighted and neglected all, and could not, according to juſtice, ſuſpend the accuſed from ſitting and acting in the Houſe: and for that there were ſecret deſignes and practices by the influence of the guiltie and their Accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to imbrolle the kingdome in a new warre, a truth now as manifeſt as the Sun. They ſay pag. 14. of that Remonſtrance,</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96497:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>That upon al theſe grounds and for al grounds,</hi> (therin) <hi>primiſed, they prould be inforced to take ſuch courſes extraordinary at God ſhould end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and direct them to, to put things to a ſpeedy iſſue</hi> the which Mr. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarer repreſents, as if the Army could by violence murther the 11. Members: for ſo that word aſſaſination imports in ſuch caſes. And now I appeale to all Judicious men, the preſedence and the ſubſequence, the premiſed reaſons and conſiderations weighed and compared, whether that ſaying of <hi>being enforced to take extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary courſes,</hi> can be adjudged a treating or commination? And truly Mr. Declarer, where ordinary meanes are inefectuall, to uſe extraordinary, is both requiſit and Lawfull. It is Juſtified in Scripture, when all warnings and wiſhings, reaſons and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells rules examples and directions would nor rectifie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme <hi>Joram</hi> and <hi>Jeſabell,</hi> you know what <hi>Jehu</hi> did, and what meanes he uſ'd: Nor can you be ignorant what the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did unto the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> after that they had uſed ordinary meanes, and demanded thoſe Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> (who had deſtroyed the Levits wife) unto juſtice and were den'ed them, Judge. 20.12.13. &amp; ſo forward. And though the general rule be, <hi>Non eundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt ad extraordinaria cùm per extraordinaria eundil eſt: fierè poteſt;</hi> yet <hi>à contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi> &amp; by neceſſary co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcquence, in al juſt caſes, <hi>Cùm per ordinaria non fiiri poteſt, ad extraordinaria eundum eſt</hi> and therefore it is beyond ſcruple or queſtion that in caſe the Army cannot obtaine their juſt and Lawfull ends by an ordinary way, they may take a courſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinaty for attaining them. But what threatning doe theſe words of the Army more emply, then thoſe of the Parliament in their petition to the King. 1. March 1647. concerning the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia:<note place="margin">Booke Declar: page 93.</note> where they ſpeak thus viz <hi>But vnles your Ma<hi rend="sup">ti</hi>, ſhal be graciouſly pleaſ'd to aſure them by theſe meſſengers that you will ſpeedily apply your Roya aſcent to the ſatiſfaction of their former deſires they ſhall be</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> 
                  <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced for the ſafety of your Majeſty and your Kingdomes to diſpoſe of the Malitia, by the authority of both houſes in ſuch a way as hath beene propounded to your Majeſty and they</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> 
                  <hi>reſolve to doe it accordingly: now</hi> was ſuch language, Lawfull then in the Parliament, (ſubjects and ſervants) to their Soveraigne: and are not the like or word to the ſame effect in the like caſe, now Lawfull in the Army, to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, who are only their truſtees, and have ſwarved from their duties much more then the King did from his, and have much
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96497:6"/>more abuſed their truſt? And if this be ſo great a fault in the Army, then <hi>à minore ad maius,</hi> much greater was that in them to the King, and thus ſtill Mr. Declarer inſtead of extenuating the accuſeds guilt, aggravates and augments it.</p>
               <p>And whereas the Declarer, in his ſaid fourth inſtance ſaith; the Army <hi>have exceeded the Kings proceedings againſt the five Members, who within five daies after retracted his charge and proceedings againſt them, and never proſecuted their ſuſpention from the houſe, which the</hi> Army <hi>preſſe and reiterate againe and againe.</hi> I anſwer; that if the King did recede or retract his charge againſt the five Members, it proves not that the five Members were innocent, no more then it argues, that becauſe a man Robbed, will not proſecute the Theife, he is guiltleſſe: nor doth, or can it condemne the Army, becauſe they are more reſolute in the proſecution againſt theſe eleven, then the King was againſt thoſe five. What if my neighbour be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to remit or pretermit a Felonie, &amp;c. for preſent, becauſe of ſome inconvenience lying in the way of proſecution, and the ſame perſon having taken thereby encouragement or advantage to rob, and ſpoyle mee; I afterwards will proſecute him thereupon to Juſtice; am I therefore injuſt? No ſure. It is injuſt to ſay it: But here I will prove that the King did never retract his charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the five Members, and that he did more then once or twice preſſe the houſe, and moſt earneſtly proſecute for their ſuſpention and reſtriction. For the firſt, <hi>page</hi> 49. booke of Declarati: The King in his meſſage to both Houſes concerning this very buſineſſe ſaith. <hi>That his</hi> Majeſtie <hi>takeing notice that ſome conceive it diſputable, whether his proceedings with the Lord</hi> Kymbolton, <hi>Mr.</hi> Hollis, <hi>&amp;c. be legal, and agreeable to the priviledges of Parliament; &amp; being very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to give ſatisfaction to all men</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is pleaſed to wave (not retract) his former proceedings, and all doubts by this meanes being ſettled, when the mindes of men are compoſed, his</hi> Majeſtie<note n="*" place="margin">Nore, and in booke Declar: page 50. In a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Meſſage the ſame words are expreſſed.</note> 
                  <hi>will proceede thereupon, in an unqueſtionable way.</hi> But this ſettlement of doubts and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure of mens mindes; it is evident Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> and others indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, prevented: by raiſing the ſtorme higher, and making the breach widder, by which meanes his <hi>Maieſty</hi> could never enter upon that unqueſtionable way, to make his Charge good againſt them. Now judge I pray you, if here was not a reſerved reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96497:6"/>in the King, of proceeding upon his charge, (and no retracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) and I am perſwaded there is ſo ſtill, if things ſettle and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre; albeit for preſent he waved it: And it followes not, becauſe I ſay I will not call upon ſuch a man this day, by reaſon it is not convenient, that I have ſaid or reſolved to call upon him no more.</p>
               <p>Here is onely proved, and the falſhood diſproved: And for the other, that the King never proſecuted the Suſpention of the five Members from the Houſe, did not the King firſt ſend a Sergeant at Armes to the Houſe, to demand and apprehend them? Secondly, did he not go Himſelfe and demand them, if they had been there, yea and ſeeing they were not there, did he not tell the Houſe that he would have them whereſoever hee found them, and did expect that they (meaning the Houſe) ſhould ſend them unto him, ſo ſoone as they returned to the Houſe? See his Majeſties ſpeech 4. <hi>January,</hi> 1641. <hi>pag.</hi> 36. <hi>book</hi> Decl. and did hee not alſo after all this goe in perſon into London to demand them of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? &amp; exhibit articles againſt them alſo? but they then, pleaded pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, as they do now, a thing I conceive <hi>Mr. Prynn</hi> can inſtance no example for, in all his reading; and thus here is another of <hi>Mr. Declarers</hi> lyes manifeſted: But by theſe infallible markes it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent that the Declaration is <hi>Mr. Prynns,</hi> whoſe naturall quality is to ly, rayle, ſcandalize and clamour. I remember <hi>Mr. Iohn Lilburne</hi> chargeth him in one of his Bookes with 13, or 14. poſitive lyes in leſſe then 8. lines, and to ſpeake truth this Declaration and his iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ification, and demands written libellouſly againſt the Army, are meerely a compoſure of lyes, calumny, forgery and ſophiſtry wherein he powers forth the poyſon and bitterneſſe of his ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Army. <hi>Oh quantum mutatus ab illo.</hi> How deſperately doth he now proſecute that way w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he formerly profeſt, &amp; thoſe whom he formerly pretended to affect, building againe that which he heretofore deſtroyed, the truth is he is Apoſtatiſed, and for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment hath forſaken the truth and much it is to bee feared God hath forſaken him. Remember <hi>Spyra Mr. Prynn</hi> &amp; that is in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.4, 5, 6. A man ye know may give his body to be burnt, and yet without charity it availeth him nothing, think not what you have ſuffer'd but conſider fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what you are faln; it is hard kicking againſt the pricks, wo be to him that is found a fighter againſt God, this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96497:7"/>being of God, as queſtionles it is to extirpate oppreſſion &amp; injuſtice and to eſtabliſh Righteouſneſſe; All the Malice, Policy and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of you and of the gates of Hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it.</p>
               <p>For that fift reaſon of <hi>Mr. Declarers,</hi> where he ſaith that the <hi>iniuſtice of the Army appeares by their uniuſt and unreaſonable demands of the Members to be ſuspended, after the Houſe had voted that it did not appeare to them there was any cauſe of ſuspenſion,</hi> &amp;c. it is reaſonles, and anſwered ſufficiently above; Had the <hi>Charge</hi> been a bare ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, confeſſe their votes had been colourable, but here was matter of fact charged upon them, and the Houſe to vote them quit without a heareing was illegall, and a meere foreſtalling of iuſtice. For his inſinuation to excite the Countys and Burroughs for which they ate Members to Petition the Houſe for them, as they did for <hi>Mr. Hampden</hi> &amp;c. it is not to be weighed, nor are they worthey of that honour or favour of their Country: the Coutryes and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs for which they ſerve, have more cauſe to petition and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune the Houſe for to admit a legall and ſpeedy tryall againſt them that they may receive iuſtice for falſifying their truſt, and betraying of the Kingdome, and I wonder with what face <hi>Mr. Declarer</hi> can attribute <hi>faithfullneſſe to their votes and advice,</hi> when as all the land knowes, that their votes advice and practiſes have been generally treaſonable, pernitious and deſtructive, but in this hee appeares a brazen faced Lawyer, who for the wages of <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> ſhall Juſtify the <hi>Deivill,</hi> and Counſell <hi>Moab</hi> againſt <hi>Jſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his fixt inſtance there is nothing materiall or obſervable, but his <hi>Malice:</hi> how willing and induſtrious he is to caſt dirt upon the Army, though it light upon his owne face; for there he chargeth them for want of more materiall matter, with <hi>bringing in their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickles on Tueſday the ſixt of</hi> July, <hi>whereas the Houſe ordered they ſhould bring them in the Friday before,</hi> was not here a great treſpaſſe and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence a high point of unreaſonablenes &amp; injuſtice? I belive the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thinke it too ſoone: and the Houſe of Commons were not ſo expeditious in delivering in their perticular charge againſt <hi>Stafford, Canterbury, and Berkly,</hi> yet kept them under reſtraint a long time before, and after many moneth ſtudy and preparation their charge was both lambe and imperfect and far below this, as low as <hi>Mr. Declarer</hi> doth declare it to be: but I am perſwaded he could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96497:7"/>to have it yet lower, even under the earth, or in the bottome of the Sea if it could be. And ſo <hi>I</hi> come to his ſeaventh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>Wherein inſtead of producing any reaſon or good argument to prove the unreaſonableneſſe of the Armyes charge and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt the eleaven Members, he fals on rayling according to <hi>Mr. Prynns.</hi> manner on certaine men <hi>Mr. Liburne, Amon Wilbee</hi> and others (inſerting <hi>Jndge Jenkins</hi> for company) and calls them <hi>Mercenary Pamphleters,</hi> only becauſe they declare the truth and avow juſtice, nor are thoſe tracts he there cenſures pamphlets but ſolid tracts or treatiſes, to informe the too much deceived people; the w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he migth do well to refute or diſprove (if he can) by ſolid argument, for reproach and clamour is neither legall nor rationall anſwer. And it is ſufficiently known to men of more integrity and leſſe corrupt in judgment then <hi>Declarer</hi> the ſhamles ſuppoſed <hi>Prynn</hi> who ſpeakes for his own <hi>Diana,</hi> that thoſe Gentle-men hee tearms <hi>mercenary,</hi> were never of ſo baſe a Spirit, for if preferment or profit would have by aſſed them or made them baſe, like him and others apoſtatiſed perſons, whereas they long have ſuffered both in their eſtates, and perſons, they might I believe long ſince have equaliz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him and other ſuch Temporizers, both in place, and power, though not in Bribery deceit and knavery: but <hi>Mr. Pryn</hi> is Chair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of a Committee, and was appointed a principall Commoner for the deforming (reforming it was ſaid) of the Vniverſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and happily the man had ſome thoughts of obtaining the <hi>Chancellours</hi> place; give him leave therefore to ſpeake for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe his fee and reward; his place, and his office and authority Committee man was therefore beſtowed upon him, it is more I am confident then <hi>Mr. Lilburn</hi> or <hi>Mr. Wilbee</hi> ever got by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and therefore juſtly may the terme of <hi>mercenary,</hi> bee retor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon himſelf, and hath he not done them good ſervice for their wages, caſting away for their ſaks both honeſty &amp; Conſcience, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and good manners, religion and wiſedome in all his writings in the behalfe of theſe Trayterous perſons (his promoters and ſupporters) and their adherents? And of late the man is raveing mad ſee his Queries his Declartion againſt the Army and their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, his Juſtification, his Vindication and full anſwer in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the eleaven juſtly accuſed <hi>Members,</hi> wherein he termes the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96497:8"/>Charge a ſcandalous <hi>Libell,</hi> and yet himſelfe the only Pamphleter and ſhameles notorious Libeller, for he ſubſcribs his name to none of theſe his papers, and if his cauſe be good what need he feare? but he is ſenſible that his eares are already ſo ſhort, they wil not ſtretch to make ſatisfaction &amp; as for the brands of L. in his cheeks ſet upon him as a Libeller though then they were unjuſt, yet now he juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, he is wiſe and loves I ſee not to weare any thing impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly or impertinently.</p>
               <p>But I will come to that paſſage in the <hi>Declarers</hi> (<hi>Prynns</hi> doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe) declaration, concerning the accuſed Members in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> and the Army June 14. laſt, and lay open unto you how this Impoſtour (after the manner of the Devill his maſter in uſing of Scripture who only takes and applyes what ſerves his purpoſe) hath taken certaine peecemeales of the Armyes Declaration out of ſeverall places of it and put them into a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſaying together in his declaration againſt them, marking them in the margent thus ☞ as a matter of ſpeciall diſcovery: by which diabollicall practice, the which few uſually will or can examine he imagens he hath ſtrucken the Army throrow, and given them an incureable wound in their reputation and honour: I will firſt give you the paſages as he cites it, and there I will open and diſect it that yee may ſee his pernicious policy, malice and vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany. He ſaith that in the ſaid Declaration of Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> and the Army page 7, 8 14. <hi>June,</hi> it is rendred thus, <hi>wee humbly deſire for the ſetling and ſecuring of our owne, and the Kingdoms common right free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome peace and ſafety: that the perſons who have abuſed the Army &amp;c. may be ſome way diſabled from doeing the like or worſe to us: and for that purpoſe may not continue in the ſame power (eſpecially as our and the Kingdomes Iudges in the higheſt truſt) but may be made incapable thereof in future &amp;c. Nor would our propoſals of this ſingly, bee free from the ſcandals and appearance of faction or deſignes, only to weaken on party (under the notion of uniuſt or oppreſſive) that we may advance another, which may be imagined more our own:</hi> which Proceedings ſince (ſaith the declarer) againſt theſe Members demonſtrate it to be a moſt reall truth. Now the Army having in page 4. of that their declaration laid downe the grounds and reaſons they had before disbanding to proceede to act ſomething in reference to their own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as private perſons and members of the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96497:8"/>and the Kingdomes freedome peace and ſafety in page 5. (not the 7. nor the 8, as he cites) they ſay thus. viz. <hi>Now haveing thus farre cleared our way in this buſineſſe: we ſhall proceede to propound ſuch things as we humbly deſire for the ſetling and ſecuring of our owne and the Kingdom's common right freedome peace, and ſafety (as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth)</hi> and then they go to particulars. As 1. <hi>that the houſes be ſpeedily purged &amp;c. ſecondly page</hi> 6. <hi>that thoſe perſons who have [in the uniuſt and high proceedings againſt the Army appeared to have the will, the confidence, credit, and power,] (all which he hath left out [to abuſe the Parliament]</hi> (the which he hath alſo left out) <hi>the Army beſides</hi> the better to bring in his praevaricated ſence, he tranſcribes it, have <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed,</hi> for, <hi>to abuſe</hi> as depending on the precedent words: and there he puts an &amp;c. and comes to theſe words, viz. <hi>may be ſome way.</hi> where as the ſence is ſtill continued thus viz <hi>to abuſe the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Army [and indanger the Kingdome in carying on ſuch things against us (while an Army)]</hi> (<hi>all which alſo is</hi> omitted) <hi>may be ſome way ſpeedily diſabled from doing the like or worſe to us</hi> [<hi>(when diaſbnded and diſperced, and in the condition of private men)</hi> or to <hi>other the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born people of England in the ſame condition with us</hi>] (all which he alſo omits becauſe it demonſtrates that they act as well for the people in generall, as for themſelves) and ſkips to viz.: <hi>and for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe may not continue in the ſame</hi> (<hi>eſpecially as ours and the Kingdomes Iudges in the higheſt truſt,</hi> but <hi>may be made incapable thereof for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and from thence pretermitting all the there intervenient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and diſcourſes, he leaps to the bottome of that 6. page and comes to theſe words viz. <hi>nor would our propoſing of this ſingly be free from the ſcandall &amp; appearance of faction or deſigne, only to weaken one party under the notio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; of uniuſt oppreſſive, that we may advance another which may be imagined more our own.</hi> And having thus omitted both precedent, concurrent &amp; ſubſequent matter, and only pickt and choſen what beſt fitted his baſe purpoſe, by which falſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till deceitfull recitation he endeavours to make the Armyes preſent juſtifiable proceedings to ſavour all ſelfe, and not to be in the leaſt feaſoned with the love of the publique, or peoples welfare, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they doe amply (as ye ſee) declare ſo; he brings in his Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiticall and ſcandalous inference and aſſertion in the cloſe of this paſſage ſaying <hi>which their proceedings ſince againſt theſe members de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate to be a moſt reall truth,</hi> but as Jeſuitically leaves out theſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96497:9"/>words of connexion: viz <hi>[Wee therefore declare]</hi> which conjoine and uſher in what the Army there imediately doe declare and lay downe, they would have further done in order to the ſetling and ſecuring of the publique, together with their own peculiar right and ſafety: as yee may ſee at large in the ſaid declaration of Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> and the Army, and this diabollicall Jeſuiticall practice and preſident of foraine falſhoods out of truths and perverting of the authours genuen words and intentions, to the belying of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour and deceiving and intraping of others, this praevericatour hath learned of that old Sophiſter and grand Machiavilion the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill who dealt in like maner with <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in Paradice, and with Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God: and truly, it ſeemes he hath been a good proficient in the Devils Schoole, for he hath very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably performed this his publique exerciſe and therefore deſerves to goe out doctor, whenſoever the Devil pleaſes: but <hi>I</hi> hope his Riddle being unfolded there is none ſo ignorant or maliciouſly wilfull as to be deluded into any prejudicate opinion through his miſty writing and unſavory railing againſt the proceedings of the honourd and ever approved Army who as aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ly and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly ſeeke the univerſall good and wellbeing of the Kingdom the King and his poſterity as conducing thereto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>And Mr. <hi>Prynn,</hi> if that be your name; Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Lilburne</hi> and <hi>Amon Wilbee</hi> dare do that you dare not by this your Declaration, and other your libellous pamphlets againſt his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and the Army: owne what they have written, and do by their ſubſcription. And I dare affirme will up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on juſt occaſion, make that good, and much more to the ſhame and horrour of you and all that abhorred party you plead for. And I doubt not but before long Mr. <hi>Wilbee</hi> or ſome other wil ring you ſuch a peale for your railing as will make ſo much of your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips eares as is left, to tingle. So farewell <hi>Rabſhakeh, Shimei's</hi> Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Conſiderable Queries concerning the railing Declarer, the eleven impeached Members, and the Cities rebellious proceedings.</head>
               <p n="1">I. WHether the Railer be not a Commiſſioner for Accompts (as Mr. <hi>Prynn is</hi>) and having for bribes, paſſed many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and falſe ccompts, as that of Sir <hi>William Lewes,</hi> and <hi>Clotwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyes</hi> probably be, and <hi>Breretons</hi> and others are ſuppoſed to bee,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96497:10"/>under the notion of being vouched, and being therefore lyable for breach of truſt, bribery, perjury and falſhood, to be queſtioned: doth it not behove him to ſtand up thus ſtiffely for theſe rotten e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven Members, and others their accomplices and confederates, in whoſe diſcharge or condemnation he is intereſted?</p>
               <p n="2">II. Whether the eleven Members, Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> that Roman <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taline</hi> and the reſt, doe not plainly argue themſelves guilty of the treaſons and treſpaſſes wherewith they ſtand charged, by craving leave to goe beyond Seas, though (as they pretend) but for ſix months? For if they were not, what needed they to ſtirre, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally after ſo much lying, boaſting, pleading and apologizing in ſpeech and print for them?</p>
               <p n="3">III. If they doe goe, whether they ever purpoſe to returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? But what need that? Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> his mother, ſon and ſiſter are gone before into <hi>France,</hi> there to prepare for him a place. Mr. <hi>Maſſey</hi> may go Trade again in <hi>Hamborough,</hi> if he hath had but the honeſty to pay the 10000 l' he brake for there, which I know hee hath in theſe wars got plunder enough to doe long ſince, and to leave himſelfe a Stock ſufficient beſides. And wealthy Sir <hi>William Waller, Clotworthy,</hi> and the reſt, it is well known have had wit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to provide againſt a wet day, &amp; to make themſelves a <hi>banck</hi> in forren parts as well as at home for they alwayes feared a flight, and now they are ready to take it.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Whether it be not an Act illegall and unjuſt, and contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to the practiſe of all judiciall Courts, to Vote any man that is charged with treaſon, felony, or any other criminall treſpaſſe, free; or at liberty to travell whither he will without baile or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize? And whether ſuch ought not rather by the Law of the Land, to be ſecured by ſafe cuſtody unto triall? And whether theſe eleven Members being at liberty have not procured all theſe new tumults and troubles?</p>
               <p n="5">V. Whether they who ſhall vote, or ſet ſuch Offenders free to depart the Kingdome before Juſtice done, are not by the Law of the Land, to be taken and adjudged principals, and to have judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life and limbe as guilty of the accuſed's crimes?</p>
               <p n="6">VI. Whether Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> was not marked with an <hi>L.</hi> in both checks for a Lay-Elder: And now finding that the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96497:11"/>Presbyterian Kingdome will downe, and himſelf in danger to loſe his government and dignity, is not growne frantick and diſtracted?</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Whether the now rebellious proceedings of the Lord Major, Sheriffes, Common Councell, and others of the City of <hi>London,</hi> to raiſe forces againſt the Army of the Kingdome without Commiſſion from the King, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to authority and command of Parliament, be not after the manner of <hi>Jack Cade</hi> and <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> indeed, and deſerve the like reward?</p>
               <p>Reſolved upon the queſtion; That they have made work for the Hang-man; and that <hi>Gregory</hi> by theſe meanes is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be well ſtored againſt next Winter with furr'd gowns. For: the Reverſing of the Votes againſt the Cities late de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Petition, and of the new Ordinance for returne of the <hi>Militia;</hi> by the Parliament on monday laſt, was no Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Act, they being thereunto enforced through im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment and violence, and is of no more value then a bond, grant, or releaſe ſealed by a man <hi>per minas,</hi> or <hi>per du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces impriſonmenti,</hi> through menaces, for feare, or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of impriſonment; And therefore all theſe military preparations and proceedings of the City, notwithſtanding mondayes Votes and Orders are not onely without, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all legall authority whatſoever. And truly in that their tumultuous proceedings on monday they not onely violated and aſſaulted the two Houſes of Parliament, but the very Majeſty and Authority of the King in Parliament. It is good therfore for ſuch as have been ſo forward in theſe mutinous courſes to repent, and deſiſt, and not proceed to runne their lives and eſtates into a ſnare, for they know not whom, nor can tell what; unleſſe it be to ſave the heads of a company of deſperate Traitors, the chiefeſt of which Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> and <hi>Stapleton</hi> have been ever exquiſite in raiſing of tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96497:11"/>&amp; commotions; witnes the Kings departing through the like affronts; nor do they do this in any affection or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Kings perſon (for then they might more eaſily have fecht him home, and reſtored him long ſince) but that under this notion they may raiſe a power to reſcue him (as they conceive) from the Army, and to gaine his perſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into poſſeſſion, that ſo having him under their power, and a force ſufficient on foot (as they think) to diſperſe or ſuppreſſe the Army, they may put their owne termes upon him, and archive their old deſigne of Presbytery and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: but I know his Majeſty is as an Angell of God for wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and diſcernes their baſe treacherous ends, and I am confident he will never intruſt himſelfe, let them ſpeak ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo highly for him, in the hands of the City &amp; Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian party, for he knows they are profeſſed foes to his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, hold a compliance and confederacy with the <hi>Scots,</hi> and are no more to be truſted, then the father of lyes, and authour of theſe their deſperate councels and rebellious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Devill.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. One queſtion more upon this emergent occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, newly occaſioned and conceived, and ſo I have done. Whether the Cities impriſoning of the two Houſes of Parliament on Monday 26. of <hi>July</hi> inſtant, and enforcing them by power to grant their traiterous demands. Did not far exceed all breach or violation of priviledge, commina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or threatning that ever the King or Army uſed, as is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt the one, &amp; falſly pretended againſt the other? And whether they have not ſo far as lyes in them utterly ſubverted the power and eſſence of Parliaments?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An anſwer to an Objection.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> 
                  <hi>The Presbyterian party are all driven out of the Houſe, ſo that there are none but Independants left, and they comply with the Army, and do what they liſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:96497:12"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> Why did the Presbyterians leave the Houſe and diſert their duties? Who drove them thence? Did any Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults or aſſaults from the Independent party in the City, or the Army? Or did not their own guilt and evill conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences? And why may not the Independant party act and comply with the Army in their juſt and lawfull demands and propoſalls to the ſettlement of the Kingdome in peace and ſafety? as well as the Presbyterian did with the City in their unjuſt and unlawfull demands and propoſalls con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the enthraldome and inſlaving of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>And note that by the Law of the Land an Abettour in any inſurrection, murder, treaſon, or rebellion, is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall, and ſhall ſo ſuffer: Looke therefore to your ſelves yee Maſters, and others, who on monday laſt animated and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betted your Apprentices and others, to impriſon and aſſault the two Houſes. Remember <hi>Stamford</hi> and <hi>Aſhenhurſt</hi> who were both condemned at Guild-hall, and hanged at Tyburn for acting in the like ſort (though in an inferiour caſe) in the Inſurrection which was many yeares ſince in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> upon an Arreſt. And was it high treaſon for the Apprentices tumultuouſly to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault the late Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterburies</hi> houſe at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> becauſe a Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, and one of them therefore ſuffered for it as a traytour? And was it high Treaſon for the <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>Eſſex</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, only to lock up ſome of her Privy Councell in his owne Study, which the Queen ſent to confer with him, and was he therefore executed? And is it not high Treaſon in a more tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent manner, tumultuouſly to aſſault, and by force to lock up and impriſon the Supreme Councell of the Kingdom, Sitting by the Kings authority in the Supreme Judicatory of the Land? Compare, conſider and judge.</p>
               <p>Remember ye proud preſumptuous Men of <hi>London,</hi> that dreadfull ſaying of our Saviour concerning <hi>Capernaum,</hi> viz. <hi>And thou Capernaum, which art exalted to heaven, ſhall be caſt downe to hell.</hi> And truly I feare yee haſten your owne deſtruction, and that the day of your humbling is at hand.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
